Elsie Ball Wright Bowley Papers WLU.Coll.0242
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
Elsie Ball Wright Bowley Papers
1929-1972
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
Bowley, Elsie Ball Wright
Du Pont, Jessie Ball
Du Pont, Alfred I. (Alfred Irénée), 1864-1935
Bowley, Albert J. (Albert Jesse)
Wright, Thomas Ball
Thompson, Tad
WLU.Coll.0242
2.5 Linear Feet
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Tad Thompson, 7/9/98.
Biographical / Historical
Elsie Ball Wright Bowley was the wife of General Albert J. Bowley, and the sister of Jessie Ball du Pont, a benefactor and Trustee of Washington and Lee.
Scope and Contents
Includes correspondence (4 folders) by and about Elsie Bowley's sister, Jessie Ball du Pont, and her brother-in-law, A. I. du Pont, as well as letters and correspondence from Elsie's son, Thomas Ball Wright, Ball family members of the Northern Neck of Virginia and other members of the du Pont family. Also contains papers of General Albert J. Bowley, along with Elsie Bowley's business papers regarding her benefactions. Includes ca. 175 photographs (mainly family photos), most of which are not identified.
Correspondence; Photographs; Ball family; Du Pont Family; Thompson, Tad
- Letters and Cards When Elsie was at Union Memorial Hospital, 1929, Ball, Edward; Doty, William K.; Butzner, William W.; Norris, Robert Opie, Jr.; Saunders, John R.; Lee, Marguerite du Pont; Edwards, Minnie; Du Pont, Maurice; Hall, Basil Wise; Haile, Ella Gresham; Yerby, Emma S.; Wright, Thomas Ball; Jesse, Eoline Ball; Lewis, James M.; Huidekoper, Bessie; Wilson, F. B., Mrs.; Lewis, Ellen; Gresham, Nannie; 38 Item (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Letters fromEdward Ball, April 24, 1929William K. Doty, April 21, 1929William W. Butzner, Apil 23, 1929John R. Saunders, May 9, 1929Marguerite du Pont LeeMinnie Edwards, April 29, 1929Maurice DuPontBasil Wise HallElla G. HaileEmma S. Yerby, April 19, 1929Thomas 'Tom' Ball Wright, April 25, 1929Eoline Ball Jesse (2 letters)James M. Lewis, May 4, 1929'Bessie' most likely Bessie HuidekoperMrs. F. B. Wilson, April 24, 1929Ellen Lewis, May 9, 1929J. Dew Bland (most likely), April 20, 1929Nannie Gresham Clift (2 letters), May 18, 1929
  Dew, J. Bland
- Letters and Cards When Elsie was at Union Memorial Hospital, cont., Lee, Marguerite du Pont; Wright, Thomas Ball; Cralle, A. A.; Adams, Edna; Doty, Margaret; Baker, Isabel Ball; Sadler, Mary; Gresham, William D.; Dew, Sarah Ford; Tucker, Elsie B.; Dickey, Sadie Crane; Lauer, Nellie; Lewis, James M.; Yerby, Emma S.; Barron, Sallie H.; Ware, Catherine E.; Reid, Mina (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Letters from:Marguerite du Pont Lee, May 8, 1929Thomas Ball Wright ('Mother's Day Greeting', 4 cards, 4 letters. Many signed 'Tucker')A. A. Calle, May 4, 1929Edna AdamsMargaret Doty, Apil 25, 1929Isabelle Baker (telegraph), April 29, 1929Mary Sadler, April 23, 1929William D. Gresham, April 24, 1929Sarah Ford Dew, April 26, 1929Elsie B. TuckerSadie Crane Dickey, May 4, 1929Nellie LauerJames M. Lewis, April 24, 1929Emma S. Yerby, May 8, 1929Sallie H. BaronCatherine E. Ware, May 21, 1929Mina Reid, June 19, 1929'Sue' (4 letters)'Alice,' April 26, 1929'Hazel,' May 16, 1929'Anne,' May 11, 1929'Elsie'
  Bowley, Elsie Ball Wright
- Miscellaneous Letters, 1928-1957; Wharton, Henry M.; Black, Elizabeth H.; Pollard, Grace; Tucker, Beverley R. (Beverley Randolph); Orbison, Thomas J. (Thomas James); Bumgardner, Eleanor; Pollard, Violet Elizabeth McDougall; Marter, Beatrice; Pollard, John Garland; Ball, Edward; Lee, Dorothy Vandegrift; McPherson, Martha E.; Butzner, William W.; Nice, Edna V.; Marshall, Katherine; Mordin, Florence; Patterson, Charles H.; Greble, Edwin St. John, Mrs.; Young, Gordon R.; Graig, Malin; 47 Item (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Letters from:Henry M. Wharton, April 21, 1928'Sadie,' August 19, 1931Elizabeth H. Black, December 10, 1931Grace Pollard, May 6, 1930 and December 26, 1931Beverley R. Tucker, August 22, 1931'Cousin Gillie' (2 letters- August 27 & December 10, 1931Thos. J. Orbison, May 25, 1933Eleanor Bumgardner, October 4, 1933Margaret Teahaw, October 8, 1933Violet 'Mac' McDougall Pollard, December 5, 1933Mrs. Dern (invitation), December 6, 1933Beatrice Marter (7 letters), October 10, 1933, March 2, April 19, 1934, December 24, 1936, February 4, 1937, November 22, 1937John Garland Pollard, August 23, 1934Edward Ball, September 20, 1934Dorothy Vandegrift Lee (2 letters, 1 card), September 3, 1931, November 3, 1936Clyde Garrett (telegraph about symphony concert), January 14, 1953Martha E. McPherson, March 26, 1937Wm. W. Butzner, July 13, 1939Edna V. Nice, November 4, 1937Governor John Garland Pollard (Christmas Card most likely when Elsie was in the hospital in 1929)Katherine MarshallFlorence MordinHattie Belle GreshamCharles H. Patterson'Mary'Mrs. E. St. John GrebleGordon R. Young, December 4, 1947Malin Craig, December 28, 1942
- Miscellaneous Letters, 1950s-1960s, 1950-1970; Rhodes, Fred Burnett, Jr.; Rhodes, Winona Henderson; Johnston, Elizabeth Nash; Whitman, Ann C.; Battle, John Stewart; England, G. A.; Palmer, Williston B.; Heflin, Charles W.; Palmer, Bruce, Jr.; Mathe, Robert E.; Shannon, John T.; Glenn, Thelma H.; McAuliffe, Anthony C., General; McAuliffe, Helen Whitman; Gresham, Louis B.; Hart, Charles Edward, Lieutenant General; Hart, Charles Edward, Mrs.; Heath, W. D.; Bertram, Laura; Petersen, Jargine; May, Marjorie; Huidekoper, Bessie; Matlack, J. M.; Dudley, Albert H., Jr., Dr.; Anderson, Mary Morris; 43 Item (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Letters from:Winona and Fred Rhodes, December, 15, 1959Lizzie Nash Johnston, December 3, 1959Ann C. Whitman, January 31, 1953John S. Battle (telegram), January 14, 1953G. A. England, August 13, 1959Gordan R. Young (2 letters), May 16, 1950, November 24, 1950Williston B. Palmer (6 letters), December 31, 1959, March 24, 1961, November 21, 1961, May 16, 1963, ebruary 19, 1968, April 28, 1868Charles W. Heflin (3 letters), February 9, 1961, February 23, 1962, February 18, 1963Bruce Palmer, Jr., February 15, 1966Robert E. Mathe, June 1, 1967John T. Shannon, October 17, 1960General and Mrs. Anthony McAuliffe, December 8, 1949Louis B. Gresham, May 4, 1967Lieutenant General and Mrs. Charles Edward Hart, September 10, 1967W. D. Heath, April 10, 1968Secretary of Lord Richard Percy, September 29, 1965Jargine Peterson, July 8, 1968'Gladys,' December 14, 1962Marjorie May (telegram), April 25, 1962Laura Bertram (4 letters), September 17, 1967'Marge,' July 22, 1968'Bessie,' most likely Bessie HuidekoperJ. M. Matlack, Jr., July 12, 1968Dr. Albert H. Dudley, Jr., July 15, 1968Mary Morris Anderson, January 5, 1968
  Bowley, Elsie Ball Wright; Percy, Richard, Lord
- Miscellaneous Letters, 1970s, 1970-1980; Bertram, Laura; Huidekoper, Bessie; 42 Item (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Many cards letters from friends and family, including Laura Bertram, Bessie, and 'Pit,' to Elsie. Also included are sympathy notes when Jessie died.
  Bowley, Elsie Ball Wright; Du Pont, Jessie Ball
- Miscellaneous Letters, 1970s, cont., 1970-1980; 45 Item (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Several letters and cards written to Mrs. Bowley by friends and family, many from neices and nephews. Some of the letters are notes of sympathy after Jessie's death.
- Ball Letters, Ball, Edward; Ball, Ruth; 54 Item (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Several letters to Elsie, Thomas, and General Bowley from different members of the Ball Family. There are many letters from Edward Ball and his wife Ruth.
- Letters from Elsie's Son, Thomas Ball Wight, 1931-1955; Wright, Thomas Ball; 24 Item (Box 2, Folder 9)
  This file contains many letters from Thomas Ball Wright to his mother, Elsie. Several of the letters are written during his times at Woodberry Forrest School and at the University of Virginia. Also included in the file are letters to Pit and Jessie.
- Letters from Cousins, Edwards, Minnie; Dew, J. Bland; Gresham, Katherine; 14 Item (Box 2, Folder 10)
  This file consists of letters to Elsie and Thomas Ball Wright from members of the Ball family, including Minnie, 'Cousin Bland,' and Katherine Gresham.
- Letters from Elsie's Nieces and Nephews, 23 Item (Box 2, Folder 11)
  This file consists of letters from Elsie's nieces and nephews, identified as such. Many of the letters are from 'Shirley' and 'Marge and John.'
- Letters from the Wrights, Palmer, Williston B.; Wright, Edgar; Wright, Rhonda M.; 6 Item (Box 2, Folder 12)
  This file contains letters from Williston B. Palmer (subject: Edgar Wright), Edgar Wright, 'George,' and Rhonda M. Wright.
- Letters from Family, Anderson, Mary Morris; Haile, Ella Gresham; Bowley, Bobbie; Yerby, Emma S.; Hoffman, Jane; Lee, Marguerite du Pont; 38 Item (Box 2, Folder 13)
  This file contains letters and telegrams from an array of people. There are several letters from Mary Morris Anderson, Ella Haile, and Emma Yerby. There is also a letter from 'Bro. Barney' and letters from members of the Hoffman Family. Elsie often had folders marked 'family.'
- Letters Written by A.I. du Pont, 1921-1935, Du Pont, Alfred I. (Alfred Irénée), 1864-1935; 23 Item (Box 3, Folder 14)
  This file consists of letters from A.I. Du Pont. to Elsie, Thomas Ball, A.J. Bowley, and Henry DeShields. There is also a 'suggested annual budget' for Alfred V. Du Pont.
  Ball, Thomas; Bowley, Elsie Ball Wright; DeShields, Henry C.; Bowley, Albert J. (Albert Jesse)
- Letters from Jessie Ball du Pont, 1917-1970; Du Pont, Jessie Ball; Williams, Hazel; 68 Item (Box 3, Folder 15)
  The letters are mostly written to Elsie, but there are letters to Edward, Thomas Ball, Belle Baker and General Bowley as well. Many of the later letters to Elsie were written by Hazel Williams on behalf of Jessie.
  Ball, Edward; Ball, Thomas; Bowley, Elsie Ball Wright
- Letters to or about Jessie Ball du Pont, Gouldin, Bessie; Dew, J. Bland; 20 Item (Box 3, Folder 16)
  This files consists of letters to or about Jessie Ball du Pont. Many of the letters are from the Alred I. du Pont Institute to Elsie. The file also consists of sympathy letters from family and friends to Elsie about Jessie's death.
  Du Pont, Jessie Ball; Bowley, Elsie Ball Wright
- Letters from du Pont Relatives, Lee, Marguerite du Pont; Zapffe, Carl A.; Zapffe, Denise; Huidekoper, Bessie; Ruoff, Madeline du Pont; Ruoff, Hermann; du Pont, Henry C.; 42 Item (Box 3, Folder 17)
  The letters are from members of the du Pont Family to Elsie.
- Benefactions and Requests, 1930s, 1930-1940; Jesse, James D.; 3 Item (Box 4, Folder 18)
  This file consists of two letters from James D. Jesse of Nuttsville, Va. and of a thank-you letter from the Woman's Club of Essex County.
- Benefactions - James Monroe Memorial Foundation, 1950s, 1950-1960; 23 Item (Box 4, Folder 19)
  This file consists of letters from the James Monroe Memorial Foundation thanking Elsie for gifts. Elsie later joined her sister Isabel in becoming a trustee of the foundation. Several meeting minutes and reports are included in the file.
  Baker, Isabel Ball; Bowley, Elsie Ball Wright
- Benefactions, 1950s, 1950-1960; 26 Item (Box 4, Folder 20)
  This file includes letters and benefactions by several different societies and associations, including The Society of the Lees of Virgina, The National Mary Washington Memorial Association, The Eisenhower-Nixon Club, and The Northern Neck of Virginia Historial Society.
- Benefactions, 1960s, 1960-1970; Randolph-Macon Woman's College; Palmer, Williston B.; United States Military Academy; St. Margaret's School (Tappahannock, Va.); Alfred I. Du Pont Institute; 47 Item (Box 4, Folder 21)
  This file consists of benefactions and several progams from events such as the Dedication of the Victorine duPont Dent Memorial Clinic and the Dedication Ceremony of the Jessie Ball duPont Library at Sewanee. There are many letters rom the St. Margaret's School in Tapahannock, Virginia and the United States Military Academy.
  University of the South. Jessie Ball duPont Library
- Benefactions, 1960s, cont., 1960-1970; Randolph-Macon Woman's College; Mary Washington College of the University of Virginia; Society of the Cincinnati in the State of Virginia; 56 Item (Box 4, Folder 22)
  This file consists of benefactions and letters from the United States Military Academy, Mary Washington College, Randolph-Macon Woman's College, and the Society of the Cincinnati in the State of Virginia.
- Benefactions - James Monroe Memorial Foundation, 1960s, 1960-1971; 17 Item (Box 4, Folder 23)
  This file consists of benefactions and documents rom the James Monroe Memorial Foundation.
- Benefactions, 1970s and no date, 1960-1970; National Society of the Colonial Dames of America in the Commonwealth of Virginia; Pollard, John Garland; Mary Washington College of the University of Virginia; 43 Item (Box 4, Folder 24)
  This file consists of benefactions from several organizations, including the British Commonwealth Nurses War Memorial Fund, Mary Washington College, and personal letters from students receiving scholarships in memory of General Bowley.
- Financial Records, 1929-1940; 47 Item (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Financial Records, 1934-1968; 30 Item (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Financial Records, 1942-1972; 19 Item (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Biography of General A. J. Bowley, 2 Item (Box 5, Folder 28)
  Bowley, Albert J. (Albert Jesse)
- General Bowley's Will, 1933; 2 Item (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Cards to General Bowley from Elsie and Jessie, no date, Bowley, Elsie Ball Wright; Du Pont, Jessie Ball; 8 Item (Box 5, Folder 30)
- Letters from General Bowley, 1943-1945; 7 Item (Box 5, Folder 31)
- Letters to or About General Bowley, 1923-1945; Haile, Ella Gresham; Wright, Thomas Ball; Huidekoper, Bessie; 56 Item (Box 5, Folder 32)
  This file consists of letters written to General Bowley and letters to Elsie about General Bowley. Most of the letters are from family and friends. General Bowley and Elsie's engagement accouncement and General Bowley's death certificate are included in this file.
- Sympathy Letters to Elsie When A.J. Bowley died, 1945-05; Anderson, Mary Morris; Palmer, Williston B.; Ralston, Betty; Read, Mary B.; Rhodes, Charles D.; Rehe, A. J., Major; Riely, Jean Roy; Lundgren, Ralph O.; 25 Item (Box 5, Folder 33)
  Bowley, Elsie Ball Wright; Bowley, Albert J. (Albert Jesse)
- Sympathy Letters to Elsie When A.J. Bowley died, cont., Parker, Katherine L.; McKnew, Thomas W.; Pratt, Sadie; Kenned, John T., Brigadier General; Kent, Alicia; Lincoln, Bertie; Lee, Mary Middleton Wilkerson; Lawrence, Shirley; Martin, Charles; 87 Item (Box 5, Folder 34)
  Sympathy notes from friends of Elsie and General Bowley. There are also many cards from flower arrangements sent to Elsie.
- Sympathy Letters, cont., 1945-05-1945-06; Ball, Emma A.; Brown, Thomas R., Dr.; Bowley, Virginia; Lee, Dorothy Vandegrift; Bowley, Bobbie; Bland, Minnie; Campbell, Alice R.; 58 Item (Box 5, Folder 35)
  More sympathy letters and cards from friends and family
  Bowley, Albert J. (Albert Jesse); Bowley, Elsie Ball Wright
- Sympathy Letters, cont., 1945-05-1945-06; Lee, Dorothy Vandegrift; Ball, Helen; Bowley, Virginia; Bowley, Bobbie; Ball, Betrand R.; Bowley, D. Gould; 70 Item (Box 5, Folder 36)
- Sympathy Letters, cont., 1945-05-1945-08; Tucker, Beverley R. (Beverley Randolph); Hoffman, Flora Bowley; Mason, Alice; Wright, Sadie; Wright, Marjorie; Gresham, Philip; Norris, Robert Opie, Jr.; Tucker, Elsie B.; 87 Item (Box 5, Folder 37)
- Sympathy Letters, cont., 1945-05-1945-09; Dew, J. Bland; du Pont, Alfred Victor; Edwards, Minnie; Gresham, Sadie; Gresham, Nellie; Gresham, Eva; Hoffman, Flora Bowley; 84 Item (Box 5, Folder 38)
- Sympathy Letters, cont., 1945-05-1945; Cauthorne, William; Dew, J. Bland; Dew, Sarah Ford; Doty, William K.; Gresham, Mary; du Pont, Margery; du Pont, Nesta; Du Pont, Marianna; 58 Item (Box 5, Folder 39)
- Invitations to Truman and Eisenhower Inaugurals, 1949-01-20; 1953-01-20; 2 Item (Box 6, Folder 40)
  Bowley, Albert J. (Albert Jesse); Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David); Truman, Harry S.
- Invitations and Programs, Palmer, Williston B.; United States Military Academy; Hoffman, Flora Bowley; 24 Item (Box 6, Folder 41)
  Marriage announcements, cards, church programs, graduation invitations, Valentine cards, Christmas cards,
  Tucker, Beverley R. (Beverley Randolph); United Confederate Veterans
- Cards, Mementos, Clippings, and Fragments, 1935-1970; 54 Item (Box 6, Folder 42)
  This file consists of newspaper and magazine clippings, progams, documents, invitations, and other miscellaneous realia.
- Poems, Lee, Marguerite du Pont; Tucker, Beverley R. (Beverley Randolph); 76 Item (Box 6, Folder 43)
  This file consists of mostly poetry cut out from newspapers. There are also typed and hand written copies of poems. There is one poem written for 'My little friend Elsie Ball.'
- Thomas Ball Estate, 1960; 1 Item (Box 6, Folder 44)
  Ball, Thomas
- Sympathy Letters to Elsie When Brother Thomas Died, 1960; Cauthorne, William; Lee, Maurice Du Pont; Anderson, Mary Morris; Huidekoper, Bessie; 18 Item (Box 6, Folder 45)
  This file consists of letters written to Elsie when her brother, Thomas Ball, died.
  Ball, Thomas; Bowley, Elsie Ball Wright
- Miscellany, Wright, Edgar; 9 Item (Box 6, Folder 46)
  Miscellaneous documents, a few letters, and a few newspaper clippings
- Ledger - Congratulatory Wires for Wedding, 1931 (Box 6)
- Ledger - Wedding Guests, 1931-09-12; 1 Item (Box 6)
- Certificates from Commonwealth of Virginia for Membership of the Board of Regents of the James Monroe Law Office, 1970-1972; 2 Item (Box 7, Folder 47)
- Photograph of A. I. du Pont (Box 7, Folder 48)
  Du Pont, Alfred I. (Alfred Irénée), 1864-1935
- Photographs of Places, Baker, Isabel Ball; 7 Item (Box 7, Folder 49)
  This file consists of photographs of places as identified on the back incluing early photographs of Miami Florida at the Everglades Hotel, likley taken by Isabel Ball Baker. It includes a photograph of Mary Ball Washington's grave and Ella Gresham Haile's grave. There are photographs dated 1931-1934 of the Bowley's home in Oahu, Hawaii, at the Schofield Barracks, and a photograph of Unity Church in Santa Ana, California.
  Florida -- Miami; Haile, Ella Gresham
- Four Photographs of Objects, 4 Item (Box 7, Folder 50)
  This file consists of four photographs. Three photographs are of pocket watches and the other is of a chandelier. One of the pocket watches is inscripted with 'to George Washington from John Wentworth Stark.'
  Washington, George
- Unidentified Photographs (most likely of Elsie and her family and friends), 1930-1970; 51 Item (Box 7, Folder 51)
  This file contains photographs ranging from 1923-1970. It includes portraits of Elsie and Thomas Ball Wright and a photograph from Palm Beach. Some of the square photographs are labled as Mrs. Du Pont's seventieth birthday in 1968.
  Du Pont, Jessie Ball; Bowley, Elsie Ball Wright; Haile, Ella Gresham; Wright, Thomas Ball
- Photographs of People (as identified on back), 1929-1961; 12 Item (Box 7, Folder 52)
  Du Pont, Alfred I. (Alfred Irénée), 1864-1935; Du Pont, Maurice; Haile, Ella Gresham; Du Pont, Jessie Ball; Baker, N. Addison; Bowley, Elsie Ball Wright
- Wedding Photographs of A. J. Bowley and Elsie Ball Wright, 1931; 10 Item (Box 7, Folder 53)
- Photographs of Places, 35 Item (Box 7, Folder 54)
  There are eleven c. late 1920s-early 1930s era photographs of Alameda, California buildings, churchs, neiborhoods, parks, etc. There are 8 inch x 10 inch interior views of an unidentified mansion and five photographic images of Sequoya Park, Eureka, California by the Freeman Art Company.
  California -- Alameda
- Photographs Pertaining to General Bowley, 23 Item (Box 7, Folder 55)
  Many of the photographs are taken in Asia
  Bowley, Albert J. (Albert Jesse); Bowley, Elsie Ball Wright; Haile, Ella Gresham; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David)
- Photographs of Thomas Ball Wright, 3 Item (Box 7, Folder 56)
  Postcards; Wright, Thomas Ball
- Photographs of Elsie and Family, 1919-1970; 33 Item (Box 7, Folder 57)
  Bowley, Elsie Ball Wright; Du Pont, Alfred I. (Alfred Irénée), 1864-1935; Du Pont, Jessie Ball
- 1940s-1950s Era Chinese Wedding Photograph, 2 Item (Box 7, Folder 58)
  One photograph was a gift to Mr. and Mrs. Bowley from Alfred and Molly Psai.
- Photographs of President Ramon Magsaysay, 1959; 3 Item (Box 7, Folder 59)
  This file consists of a photograph of President Magsaysay and Pedro Paguio given to Isabel Baker on June 23, 1959. There is also a print of President Magsaysay indicated that it was acquired during Mrs. Baker's visit to Manila, Philippines in 1959, and there is an itenerary of the trip.
  Philippines -- Manila; Magsaysay, Ramon; Baker, Isabel Ball
- Soft Leather Decorative (Bi-fold) Photo/Document Frames, 3 Item (Box 7)